Finding Aid for Fred L. Crawford papers, 1925-1953
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Fred L. Crawford papers 1925-1953
Crawford, Fred L., 1888-1957.
1 oversize volumes
6 linear feet
851031 Aa 2; AC
Saginaw, Michigan, sugar processor and Republican Congressman (1935-1953). Correspondence, newspaper clippings, scrapbooks, speeches, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Fred L. Crawford (donor no. 4210 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Fred Lewis Crawford, a member of Congress from Michigan, was born in Dublin, Erath County, Tex. on May 5, 1888. Before entering Congress, Crawford was in the sugar beet business, building, financing, and operating beet sugar mills in various sections of the country. He was elected as a Republican to the US Congress in 1934 and served until January 3, 1953. He was an unsuccessful candidate for re-nomination in 1952. He died in Washington, D.C. on April 13, 1957.
The Crawford collection consists of correspondence relating to his political career, especially the election campaigns of 1936, 1940 and 1952. Some of his correspondents include Wilber M. Brucker, Mar. 6, 1937, Leonard Hall, May 19, 1950, and George A. Malcolm, Nov. 7, 1936. Of note are letters of Stanley Morse of the Farmer's Independence Council, Aug.-Dec. 1935-1936, describing agricultural conditions and a letter of H.W. Anderson, April 27, 1937, relating to the Flint Sit-Down strike.
There are also scrapbooks relating to his career activities and to his trips to the Philippines in 1935 and 1946. One of his scrapbooks concerns the activities of the Federal Bureau of Investigation in 1938, and includes a letter from J. Edgar Hoover; another scrapbook contains newspaper clippings and campaign miscellanea from his re-election campaign in 1936.
The Photographs series consists of a photograph album, 1946, detailing his participation as member of the U.S. delegation to the Philippine Commonwealth and Independence ceremonies. This volume also includes photos of various countries visited on the way to and from the Philippines. Other photographs are of a Congressional visit to United States Pacific Ocean island possessions and trusts and to Japan in 1949; and portraits of other Michigan members of Congress.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Beet sugar.; Beets.; Bentley, Alvin M. (Alvin Morell), 1918-1969.; Crawford, Fred L., 1888-1957.; Farmer's Independence Council.; Michigan--Politics and government--1929-1938.; Michigan--Politics and government--1939-1945.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan Sugar Company.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.; Presidents--United States--Election--1952.; Republican Party (Mich.); Saginaw (Mich.); Strikes and lockouts--Michigan--Flint.; United States. Congress.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1936.; United States. Congress--Elections, 1940.; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation.; United States--Politics and government--1929-1933.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953.; Sit-down strikes--Michigan--Flint.; General Motors Corporation Sit-Down Strike, 1936-1937.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bennett, John B. (John Bonifas), 1905-1964.; Crawford, Fred L., 1888-1957.; Japan.; Legislators--Michigan.; Mapes, Carl Edgar, 1874-1939.; Philippines--History--1946-1986.; Shafer, Paul W. (Paul Werntz), 1893-1954.; Travel.; United States. Congress. House.; Wolcott, Jesse Paine, 1893-1969.
Contributors:
Brucker, Wilber Marion, 1894-1968.; Hall, Leonard W. (Leonard Wood), 1900-1979; Hoover, J. Edgar (John Edgar), 1895-1972.; Malcolm, George A. (George Arthur), 1881-1961.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence and other business papers
  - Undated 1925-1951, 49 folders (Box 1)
  - 1952, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - February-April 1952 (Box 2)
  - May-July 1952 (Box 2)
  - August-December 1952 (Box 2)
- Michigan Sugar Company
  - Papers 1932-1936, 5 folders (Box 2)
- Campaign and Congressional papers
  - Primary Election Results September 1938 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings concerning the primary election 1952, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Speeches, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Congressional Record Remarks
    - 1942 (Box 2)
    - 1943 (Box 2)
    - 1944 (Box 2)
    - 1945 (Box 2)
    - 1946 (Box 2)
    - 1947 (Box 2)
    - 1948 (Box 2)
    - 1950 (Box 2)
    - 1951 (Box 2)
    - 1952 (Box 2)
  - Bills introduced by Crawford 1935-1937 (Box 2)
  - The Republican Reporter, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - Constitution of Puerto Rico 1952 (Box 2)
    (autographed by dignitary)
- Scrapbooks
  - General
    - 1935 (Box 3)
    - 1936 (Box 3)
    - 1937 (Box 3)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 3)
    - 1939 (Box 3)
    - 1943 (Box 3)
    - 1944 (Box 4)
    - 1945 (Box 4)
    - 1947 (Box 4)
    - 1947-1948 (Box 4)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 4)
    - 1951 (Box 4)
  - Form letters
    - 1935-1939 (Box 5)
    - 1943-1946 (Box 5)
    - 1947-1951 (Box 5)
  - Trip to the Orient 1935 (Box 5)
    (include memorabilia, programs, and scattered photographs)
  - Reelection campaign 1936 (Volume 1)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation 1938 (Box 6)
    (includes J. Edgar Hoover letter)
  - Congressional Secretaries Club 1939-1940 (Box 6)
  - Digest of Proceedings of Congress 1937-1940 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook on the Puerto Rican inquiry 1943 (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook on around the world trip 1946 (Box 6)
- Photographs
  - Photograph album from around the world trip 1946 (Box 6)
  - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 6)